A Guide to the Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers, 1929-1998
Washington and Lee University, School of Law, Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives
- Personal Papers 1921-1996
  - Speeches, Statements, and Writings 1937-1971
    - Speeches, Statements and Writings
      - Statement on Behalf of the School Board Supporting Construction of the New High Schools Without Delay, May 6, 1959 (Box-folder 112/18)
      - Soviet Legality, July 6, 1959 (Box-folder 112/19)
        Optimist Club, Richmond, Virginia
      - Hypothetical Virginia Tour for Russian Visitors, July 21, 1959 (Box-folder 112/20)
        Notes for Guy Friddell's Program. Used as rough notes for radio programs on 7/27 & 8/3 on WRNL.
      - Introduction of James C. Sargent, August 7, 1959 (Box-folder 112/21)
        Virginia Bar Association, Greenbrier, West Virginia.
      - Legal Education, August 1959 (Box-folder 112/22)
        Notes for Virinia Bar Association panel on legal education, Greenbrier, West Virginia.
      - American Bar Association Meeting, August 1959 (Box-folder 112/23)
        Miami Beach, Florida
      - Convocation of Teachers, September 2, 1959 (Box-folder 112/24)
      - How Peaceful Is the Soviet Union?, September 15, 1959 (Box-folder 112/25)
        Junior Chamber of Commerce, Richmond, Virginia
      - Soviet Union As a Challenge to Western Civilization, September 22, 1959 (Box-folder 112/26)
        Chesapeak Corporation of Virginia, West Point, Virginia
      - Self-Employed Individuals Retirement Act, December 15, 1959 (Box-folder 112/27)
      - The Pornographic Problem In Perspective, February 2, 1960 (?) (Box-folder 112/28)
        Notes for panel discussion sponsored by Junior League, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Statement Before Senate Finance Committee on Needs for Education, February 5, 1960 (Box-folder 112/29)
      - Deans of the Washington and Lee University School of Law, March 1960 (Box-folder 112/30)
        Lexington, Virginia
      - What Should Our Students Know and Understand About the Communist System?, April 26, 1960 (Box-folder 112/31)
        Notes on panel program. National School Boards Association Meeting, Chicago, Illinois.
      - Sources of Soviet Power, May 12, 1960 (Box-folder 112/32)
        Notes for speech at Hampden-Sydney College.
      - Statement In Support Of Proposal To Teach International Communism, August 26, 1960 (Box-folder 112/33)
        House of Delegates, American Bar Association.
      - Supplemental Resolutions to those proposed by Committee on Communist Tactics, Strategy & Objectives, August 29, 1960 (Box-folder 112/34)
      - Withdrawal Of Connally Reservation, August 31, 1960 (Box-folder 112/35)
      - Convocation of Richmond School Teachers, October 6, 1960 (Box-folder 112/36)
      - The Challenge of School Board Membership, October 7, 1960 (Box-folder 112/37)
        Virginia School Board Association Annual Meeting, Roanoke, Virginia.
      - Revised Resolution of the Committee on Communist Tactics, Strategy and Objectives, October 14, 1960 (Box-folder 112/38)
      - Re: Resolution as to Teaching of International Communism, October 18, 1960 (Box-folder 112/39)
      - Public Responsibility, December 14, 1960 (Box-folder 112/40)
        Lecture to Associates. Hunton & Williams, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Patriotism - A Diluted Commodity, October 29, 1960 (Box-folder 112/41)
        Investment Bankers Association of America, Southeastern Group, Hot Springs, Virginia.
      - Education on Communism, November 30, 1960 (Box-folder 112/42)
        St. Stephen's Church.
      - George Wythe High School Dedication, December 11, 1960 (Box-folder 112/43)
      - Supplemental Statement to Virginia Commission on Public Education, December 13, 1960 (Box-folder 112/44)
      - 15 Years Have Transformed Our World, January 12, 1961 (Box-folder 113/1)
        Northside Teachers.
      - Instruction on International Communism, January 18, 1961 (Box-folder 113/2-3)
        Richmond Public School System.
      - The Need For Instruction On International Communism, January 26, 1961 (Box-folder 113/4)
        ABA Committee Conference with Educators, Washington, DC.
      - Action to Improve the Status of Lawyers, March 3, 1961 (Box-folder 113/5)
        Vermont Bar Association
      - The Need to Know the Truth About Communism, March 20, 1961 (Box-folder 113/6)
        Lecture to Senior Government Classes, George Wythe High School.
      - Soviet Education, April 19, 1961 (Box-folder 113/7)
        Southeastern Association of School Business Officials, Richmond, Virginia.
      - The Social Sciences and America's Position In World Affairs, April 29,1961 (Box-folder 113/8)
        Virginia Social Science Associations, University of Virginia.
      - Introduction of General Maxwell D. Taylor, May 7, 1961 (Box-folder 113/9)
        Commemorative Ceremony in honor of General Lee, Stratford Hall.
      - Briefing of ABA Committee on Communist Tactics by the F. B. I., September 27, 1961 (Box-folder 113/10)
        Washington, DC
      - Economics of the Legal Profession, October 12 & 13, 1961 (Box-folder 113/11)
        Virginia Bar Institute. Includes some research materials.
      - Re Economics of Legal Profession, October 21, 1960 (Box-folder 113/12)
        New Mexico Bar.
      - Bar Economics, November 29, 1960 (Box-folder 113/13)
        Oklahoma Bar Association
      - Economic Status of Legal Profession, December 21, 1961 (Box-folder 113/14)
        Delaware Bar Association
      - Instruction On Communism and Its Contrast With Liberty Under Law, January 1962 (Box-folder 113/15)
        Pamphlet published by the American Bar Association.
      - Instruction On Communism and It's Contrast With Liberty, January, 1962 (Box-folder 113/16)
        Printed booklet format.
      - Instruction On Communism - An Educational Need and Responsibility, April 6, 1962 (Box-folder 113/17)
        Prepared for Delivery to Strategy Seminar of Omaha Chamber of commerce, Omaha, Nebraska
      - Unsatisfactory Economic Status of Lawyers, April 24, 1962 (Box-folder 113/18)
        Knoxville Bar Association
      - Higher Education - Soviet Style, April 27, 1962 (Box-folder 113/19)
        Federal Bar Association, Washington, DC
      - Introduction of Dr. Charles Malik, July 6, 1962 (Box-folder 113/20)
        Virginia Bar Association
      - Instruction on Communism - What the Bar Can Do, August 4, 1962 (Box-folder 113/21)
        National Conference of Bar Presidents. Golden Gate Room, Del Webb Towne House.
      - Verbal Report to (ABA) House of Delegates, August 8, 1962 (Box-folder 113/22)
        Committee on Education In the Contrast Between Liberty Under Law and Communism
      - The Conflict We Are Losing, September 23, 1962 (Box-folder 113/23)
        Grace Covenant Church, Richmond, Virginia
      - Introduction of Floyd d. Gottwald, September 27, 1962 (Box-folder 113/24)
        Newcomen Society Dinner, Richmond, Virginia
      - Education On Communism - What the Bar Can Do, October 4, 1962 (Box-folder 113/25)
        Connecticut State Bar Association, Hartford, Connecticut
      - Teaching the Facts About Communism -- Progress In Virginia, October 17, 1962 (Box-folder 113/26)
        Virginia Parents-Teachers Association, Richmond, Virginia
      - Educational Research - a New Opportunity In Virginia, November 1, 1962 (Box-folder 113/27)
        Virginia Education Association, Richmond, Virginia
      - What State Bar Economics Committees Can Do, January 28, 1963 (Box-folder 113/28)
        To be reviewed and placed in final form by ABA Committee on Economics of Law Practice
      - The War Called Peace, February 12, 1963 (Box-folder 113/29)
        St. Christopher School, Richmond, Virginia
      - Effective Communication - A Necessary Skill, April 1, 1963 (Box-folder 113/30)
        Law School, University of South Carolina, Columbia, South Carolina
      - Education On Communism - Some Misconceptions, May 3, 1963 (Box-folder 113/31)
        Florida State Bar, Miami, Florida
      - Is There A Mellowing of Communism?, May 7, 1963 (Box-folder 113/32)
        Society of Sons of Colonial Wars, Richmond, Virginia
      - Statement In Support of J. Lindsay Almond, Jr.'s Nomination As Judge, May 24, 1963 (Box-folder 113/33)
        Judiciary Committee of United States Senate
      - How To Improve Lawyers Income, June 20, 1963 (Box-folder 113/34)
        Mississippi State Bar, Jackson, Mississippi
      - Three Giants of the Law, July 22, 1963 (Box-folder 114/1)
        Federal Bar Foundation, Washington, DC
      - Utility of the Law, August 5, 1963 (Box-folder 114/2)
        NACCA Convention, Minneapolis, Minnesota
      - How To Improve Lawyers Income, August, 1963 (Box-folder 114/3)
        ABA Meeting, Chicago, Illinois
      - Special Award To the State of Virginia, October 7, 1963 (Box-folder 114/4)
        Given by Traffic Court Program of the American Bar Association; Richmond, Virginia
      - Reflections On the Crime Problem, October 24, 1963 (Box-folder 114/5)
        Kiwanis Club, Washington, DC
      - Public Interest In Sound Bar Economics, October 31, 1963 (Box-folder 114/6)
        Allegheny County Bar Association
      - American Bar Statement Deplores Proposals To Televise Ruby Trial, December 7, 1963 (Box-folder 114/7)
        Press release. Substantially as prepared by L.F.P., Jr. and approved by Board of Governors of ABA.
      - False Facade of Peaceful Coexistence, January 21, 1964 (Box-folder 114/8)
        Woman's Club, Richmond, Virginia.
      - The Legal Profession, February 12, 1964 (Box-folder 114/9)
        Memo to W. Tayloe Murphy, Jr. asking for draft of speech.
      - Law Day - 1964, March 6, 1964 (Box-folder 114/10)
        Prepared for publication in Lawyers Title News
      - Crisis In Law Observance, March 10, 1964 (Box-folder 114/11)
        Conference of National Organizations, Chicago, Illinois.
      - Reflections On the Crime Problem, April 14, 1964 (Box-folder 114/12)
        LAMP, Cleveland, Ohio
      - Why ABA Encourages Instruction On Communism, April 15, 1964 (Box-folder 114/13)
        Statement by Lewis F. Powell Jr.
      - Educating Lawyers For Public Responsibility, April 18, 1964 (Box-folder 114/14)
        Howard College, Birmingham, Alabama
      - Is the Organized Bar Meeting Its Responsibilities?, April 22, 1964 (Box-folder 114/15)
        Kentucky State Bar Association, Louisville, Kentucky
      - Law Day - A Time For Rededication, May 1, 1964 (Box-folder 114/16)
        South Carolina Bar
      - Peaceful Coexistence - Myth Or Reality, May 26, 1964 (Box-folder 114/17)
        Town Hall, New York City
      - Objectives Of Going To College, June 5, 1964 (Box-folder 114/18)
        Country Day School for Girls, Virginia Beach, Virginia
      - Education For World Leadership - Role Of the Organized Bar, June 25, 1964 (Box-folder 114/19)
        Pennsylvania Bar Association, Erie, Pennsylvania
      - The Challenge To the Profession, August 7, 1964 (Box-folder 114/20)
        National Institute of Bar Public Relations, Waldorf Hotel, New York
      - Re-Evaluation of Canons of Ethics, August 11, 1964 (Box-folder 114/21)
        ABA House of Delegates, New York, City
      - Remarks Accepting Presidency, August 13, 1964 (Box-folder 114/22)
        Annual Banquet, American Bar Association, New York, NY
      - Areas of Emphasis For 1964/65, August 14, 1964 (Box-folder 114/23-24)
        House of Delegates, American Bar Association, New York, NY
      - A Serious Constitutional Gap - The Problem of Presidential Inability and Succession, August 28, 1964 (Box-folder 114/25)
        Jamestown Foundation
      - Notes for Panel Discussion On Federal Limitations On Attorneys' Fees, September 10, 1964 (Box-folder 115/1)
        Federal Bar Association
      - Indiana Bar - Introductory Remarks, September 18, 1964 (Box-folder 115/2)
        Indiana State Bar Association, Fort Wayne, Indiana
      - A Serious Constitutional Gap - The Problem of Presidential Inability and Vice Presidential Vacancy, September 25, 1964 (Box-folder 115/3)
        State Bar of Michigan, Grand Rapids, Michigan
      - The President's Page Sept. 1964 - Feb. 1965 (Box-folder 115/4)
        Column in ABA Journal, volumes 50 - 51
      - A Fresh Look At Professional Ethics, October 2, 1964 (Box-folder 115/5)
        State Bar New Mexico, Santa Fe, New Mexico
      - Ethical Standards of the Bar, October 22, 1964 (Box-folder 115/6)
        ABA Regional Meeting, Atlanta, Georgia
      - Remarks at Dedication of New Law School Building, October 29, 1964 (Box-folder 115/7)
        Boston University
      - Areas of Emphasis By the ABA, November 12, 1964 (Box-folder 115/8)
        Excerpts of talk to Nebraska Bar Association
      - The Risk of Having No President, December 4, 1964 (Box-folder 115/9)
        Oklahoma Bar Association, Tulsa, Oklahoma
      - A Lawyer Looks at the Crime Problem, December 9, 1964 (Box-folder 115/10)
        American Farm Bureau Federation
      - The Right to a Fair Trial, December 15, 1964 (Box-folder 115/11)
        Texas Bill of Rights Foundation, Houston, Texas
      - Legal Education for Professional Responsibility, December 28, 1964 (Box-folder 115/12)
        Association of American Law Schools, Chicago, Illinois
      - The Right to a Fair Trial, January 11, 1965 (Box-folder 115/13)
        Dade County Bar Association, Miami, Florida
      - Standards For Criminal Justice, January 15, 1965 (Box-folder 115/14)
        Maryland State Bar Association, Baltimore, Maryland
      - Introductory Comments, February 7, 1965 (Box-folder 115/15)
        ABA House of Delegates, New Orleans, Louisiana
      - The Right to a Fair Trial, February 13, 1965 (Box-folder 115/16)
        Charter Day Conference on Magna Carta Anniversary, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia. Published version is also in this file.
      - Extending Legal Services to Indigents and Low Income Groups, March, 1965 (Box-folder 115/17)
        Cleveland Bar Association
      - Educational Television - Program On Communism, March 14, 1965 (Box-folder 115/18)
      - More Effective Criminal Justice - An Urgent Need, March 21, 1965 (Box-folder 115/19)
        New York Bar speech of January 29, 1965, revised for submission to ABA Journal
      - The Deteriorating State of Law and Order, March 23, 1965 (Box-folder 115/20)
        San Francisco Bar Association and Lawyers Club of San Francisco
      - Extending Legal Services to Indigents and Low Income Groups, March 25, 1965 (Box-folder 115/21)
        Los Angeles County Bar Association
      - The Risk of Having No President, March 29, 1965 (Box-folder 115/22)
        Southeastern Electric Exchange, Boca Raton, Florida
      - State of Criminal Justice/Minimum Standards For Criminal Justice, April 5, 1965 (Box-folder 116/1)
        American College of Trial Lawyers, Biloxi, Mississippi
      - Respect For Law and Order - The Foundation of a Free Society, April 26, 1965 (Box-folder 116/2)
        University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida. University of Florida Law Review published version is entitled, Respect for Law and Due Process - The Foundation of Free Society
      - Uphold the Law: A Citizen's First Duty, May 1, 1965 (Box-folder 116/3)
        Dedication of Bar Center, Jefferson, Missouri
      - Providing Counsel For Indigent Defendants, May 24, 1965 (Box-folder 116/4)
        Joint Meeting ABA and IABA, San Juan, Puerto Rico
      - An Urgent Need: More Effective Criminal Justice, May 1965 (Box-folder 116/5)
        51 ABA Journal 437 (May 1965). Based on address to New York Bar Association, January 29, 1965.
      - 750th Anniversary of Magna Carta, June 15, 1965 (Box-folder 116/6)
        Great Hall of the Law Courts, London, England.
      - Law and Poverty, June 25, 1965 (Box-folder 116/7)
        National Conference on Law and Poverty
      - State Of Criminal Justice, June 26, 1965 (Box-folder 116/8)
        Fourth Circuit Judicial Conference, White Sulpher Springs, West Virginia
      - State of Law and Order, July 1, 1965 (Box-folder 116/9)
        State Bar of Texas, Fort Worth, Texas
      - Introduction of Senator Thomas J. Dodd, July 10, 1965 (Box-folder 116/10)
        Virginia State Bar Association, Hot Springs, Virginia
      - Jury Trial of Crimes, July 15, 1965 (Box-folder 116/11)
        Ninth Circuit Judicial Conference, Sun Valley, Idaho. Version published in 23 Washington and Lee Law Review 1 (Spring 1966, is also in this file.
      - State of the Legal Profession, August 9, 1965 (Box-folder 116/12)
        ABA President's Annual Address, Miami Beach, Florida.
      - The Need For Character Fitness In Law Students, August 10, 1965 (Box-folder 116/13)
        ABA Section of Legal Education, Miami Beach, Florida
      - Reconciling Free Press With Fair Trial, September 1, 1965 (Box-folder 116/14)
        Canadian Bar Association, Toronto, Canada
      - Reform of Criminal Justice, October 5, 1965 (Box-folder 116/15)
        University of Richmond Law School
      - Civil Disobedience vs. the Rule of Law, October 11, 1965 (Box-folder 116/16)
        Union Theological Seminary, Richmond, Virginia
      - Crime and Criminal Justice, October 26, 1965 (Box-folder 116/17)
        Yale Political Union, New Haven, Connecticut
      - Response At Testimonial Dinner, November 18, 1965 (Box-folder 116/18)
        Commonwealth Club, Richmond, Virginia
      - Duties and Powers of the State Board of Education with Respect to Educational Television Programs, December 27, 1965 (Box-folder 116/19)
      - Ceremony in Honor of T. Gray Haddon, January 3, 1966 (Box-folder 116/20)
      - Notes for Response, February 3, 1966 (Box-folder 116/21)
        Harvard Club of Virginia
      - The New Left On the Campus February 25, 1966 (Box-folder 116/22)
        Virginia Association of Colleges, Arlington, Virginia
      - the Crime Crisis and Law Enforcement April 4, 1966 (Box-folder 116/23)
        Virginia State Crime Clinic, Richmond, Virginia
      - A Lawyer Looks At Civil Disobedience April 1966 (Box-folder 116/24)
        23 Washington and Lee Law Review 205 (Fall 1966).
      - Notes for Law Day Speech May 2, 1966 (Box-folder 116/25)
        Richmond Kiwanis Club, Richmond, Virginia
      - The Disordered Society September 16, 1966 (Box-folder 116/26)
        Virginia Manufacturers Association, Williamsburg, Virginia. Printed version ( Building Respect For Law and Order) also in this file.
      - A Virginia Tradition October 4, 1966 (Box-folder 116/27)
        Key-note speech, opening of Democratic headquarters of Byrd-Spong campaign.
      - Limitations On the Right To Demonstrate October 21, 1966 (Box-folder 116/28)
        Founder's Day, Wake Forest College, Winston Salem, North Carolina.
      - Development/Retention of Law Practice November 22, 1966 (Box-folder 116/29)
        Lecture to firm of Hunton & Williams, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Wiretapping December 13, 1966 (Box-folder 116/30)
        Crime Commission office memorandum.
      - The Challenge to the Private Preparatory School January 31, 1967 (Box-folder 117/1)
      - Inadequate Discipline - A Failure of Professional Responsibility February 10, 1967 (Box-folder 2)
        National Conference of Bar Presidents, Houston, Texas.
      - Organized Crime - Challenge To a Free Society May 13, 1967 (Box-folder 117/3)
        The Business Council, The Homestead, Hot Springs, Virginia.
      - Comments At Banquet, May 20, 1967 (Box-folder 117/4)
        Harvard Law School Class Reunion.
      - Notes re crime statistics, May 1967 (Box-folder 117/5)
        Tories (?) Club.
      - Trends In Antitrust, June 17, 1967 (Box-folder 117/6)
        Conference of Financial Executives, Williamsburg, Virginia.
      - Book Review: The Suspect and Society, September 4, 1967 (Box-folder 117/7)
        Review of book by Walter V. Schaefer for ABA Journal, c. Nov. 1967.
      - Strategic Balance of Power, September 5, 1967 (Box-folder 117/8)
        Richmond Jaycees
      - Civil Disobedience: Prelude To Revolution, October 5, 1967 (Box-folder 117/9)
        Southern Company Conference of Directors and Executives, Clear Point, Alabama. Printed version from U.S. News & World Report, Oct. 30, 1967 is also in this file.
      - Statement To House Of Delegates On Reardon Committee Proposals, February 19, 1968 (Box-folder 117/10)
        American Bar Association.
      - Introduction of Dumas Malone, March 7, 1968 (Box-folder 117/11)
        Phi Beta Kappa Lecture, University of Virginia.
      - Book Review: Peace and the Strategy Conflict, by William R. Kintner, April 4, 1968 (Box-folder 117/12)
        Published in the Richmond Times-Dispatch.
      - Interview re Crime In United States, April 16, 1968 (Box-folder 117/13)
        For Dun's Review.
      - Anarchy On Campus, May 20, 1968 (Box-folder 117/14)
        Three different printed versions of the speech delivered at the 62nd Annual Convention Virginia Retail Merchants Association, Harrisonburg, Virginia.
      - Citizenship Education As To Law, Disorder, Extremism and Civil Disobedience, July 19, 1968 (Box-folder 117/15)
        A Project Approved by the Virginia State Board of Education. Printed version also in this file.
      - A Strategy For Campus Peace, November 11, 1968 (Box-folder 117/16)
        American Association of State Colleges and Universities, Washington, DC.
      - A Lawyer Looks At Directors' Responsibilities, December 5, 1968 (Box-folder 117/17)
        Bank Directors Seminar, University of Virginia.
      - 15 Years Have Transformed Our World, January 12, 1969 (Box-folder 117/18)
        Northside Teachers, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Reflections On the State of Public Education, February 7, 1969 (Box-folder 117/19)
        Virginia State Board of Education.
      - Virginia's Need For Modern Debt Provisions, February 24, 1969 (Box-folder 117/20)
        Richmond Kiwanis Club.
      - Radical Left Movement, February 27, 1969 (Box-folder 117/21)
        Chamber of Commerce, Kenbridge, Virginia.
      - Introduction of Justice Brennan, May 16, 1969 (Box-folder 117/22)
        Virginia State Bar.
      - Introduction of Fred G. Pollard, June 16, 1969 (Box-folder 117/23)
        Candidate for Virginia Governor.
      - Evaluation of Ethical Standards, August 12, 1968 (Box-folder 117/24)
        American Bar Association House of Delegates, Dallas, Texas.
      - Alienation of the Campus From National Defense, October 3, 1969 (Box-folder 117/25)
        Thomas Jefferson Award Speech, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Judge C. H. Morrissett, February 2, 1970 (Box-folder 117/26)
        Testimonial dinner for Judge C. H. Morrissett.
      - Comments On the Vietnamese War, February 11, 1970 (Box-folder 117/27)
        Public meeting, Richmond Junior League, Richmond, Virginia.
      - Geoffrey C. Hazard, Jr., February 22, 1970 (Box-folder 117/28)
        American Bar Foundation Breakfast.
      - What Is Right About America, April 16, 1970 (Box-folder 117/29)
        Key Club, Thomas Jefferson High School, Richmond, Virginia.
      - An Education FOR America, May 28, 1970 (Box-folder 117/30)
        Confidential Memorandum.
      - Political Warfare, June 30, 1970 (Box-folder 117/31)
        As submitted to President Nixon on a Confidential Basis while serving as member of Blue Ribbon Defense Panel.
      - The Attack On American Institutions, July 15, 1970 (Box-folder 118/1)
        Southern Industrial Relations Conference, Blue Mountain, North Carolina.
      - Swann v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg Board of Education, October 7, 1970 (Box-folder 118/2)
        Prepared as notes for argument, but oral argument not allowed by the Supreme Court.
      - The Overriding Issue, October 30, 1970 (Box-folder 118/3)
        Remarks in support of Sen. Harry F. Byrd, Richmond, Virginia.